Finding Aid of the Student Wisconsin Education Association at UW-Milwaukee Records
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Student Wisconsin Education Association at UW-Milwaukee Records, 2000-2011
Student Wisconsin Education Association at UW-Milwaukee
UWM Manuscript Collection 348
1.6 cubic feet (3 boxes) 147 digital files (9 GB)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
This collection documents the activities of the Student Wisconsin Education Association from 2000-2011. The majority of the documents are in scrapbook format, which highlights the group's outreach events such as Read Across America and Toys for Tots, as well as its board members. The collection also holds records for the Urban Teacher World Milwaukee program, which provides information about the program and their events for students.
The Student Wisconsin Education Association (SWEA) at UWM was a branch of the National Education Association (NEA), founded in 1937, which assists student teachers in engaging in their communities and offers professional development opportunities. In the 2003-2004 academic year, the NEA presented the UWM chapter with two national awards: the Local Excellence Award, for its professional development opportunities and community outreach events; and the Outstanding CLASS Project Award, for their chapter book about group activities and their impact on the community. The group became defunct in 2016.
The majority of the items in the collection are in scrapbook format, highlighting the group's various events and members. Other documents include fliers for events, presentation proposals, and itineraries for events. One particular program highlighted is Urban Teacher World-Milwaukee, which was designed to encourage students in urban areas to pursue a career in education. The DVDs and electronic files listed originated from these folders, and include publicity for each year's program, as well as copies of the various presentations created by students from 2003-2011.
The files are organized alphabetically by subject, then chronologically.
A spreadsheet containing additional information about the electronic records is available in the Archives.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee School of Education Records UWM Archival Collection 5
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
After the UWM Chapter of SWEA disbanded in 2016, the scrapbooks and other administrative records of the organization were held in custody by the UWM School of Education Office of Student Services.
Robert Longwell-Grice donated the materials (accession 2016-013) to the Archives on behalf of the UWM School of Education.
As of March 2017, all files were accessible on a Intel Core i5-4570 CPU (3.20 GHz, 4 GB RAM) running Windows 7, with Service Pack 1. Microsoft Office 2016, Windows Picture and Fax Viewer, and VLC media player were used to view the files.
The collection contains files in the following formats:
Microsoft Word document 97-2003 [.doc]
Microsoft Powerpoint Presentation 97-2003 [.ppt]
Windows Media Video [.wmv]
Acrobat PDF 1.3-1.4 [.pdf]
Tagged Image File Format [.tif]
MPEG-2 Program Stream [.mpg]
JPEG File Interchange Format [.jpg]
Contents List
- Records, 2000-2011, UWM Manuscript Collection 348; 1.6 cubic feet (3 boxes) 147 digital files (9 GB)
  - Activities & Scrapbook, 2002-2011 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Executive Board, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 2004-2009 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Staff Advisory Committee, 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Transition Binder, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Urban Teacher World
    - 2000-2011 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Outreach Presentation, 2007 (Electronic \Outreach_Presentation_2007\)
    - Student Projects
      - 2003 (Electronic \Urban_Teacher_World_June_22_2003\)
      - 2004 (Electronic \Urban_Teacher_World_2004\)
      - 2005 (Electronic \Urban_Teacher_World_2005\)
      - 2006 (Electronic \Urban_Teacher_World_2006\)
      - 2007 (Electronic \UrbanTeachWrld07\)
      - 2009 (Electronic \Urban_Teacher_World_2009\)
      - 2010 (Electronic \UTW2010\)
      - 2011 (Electronic \UTW2011\)
  - YES in MPS, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)